14

What Is the Occult?

One main channel through which demons gain access to humanity is the occult. If we do not understand the almost universal influence of the occult on the human race, we will not be able to deal effectively with demons.

Somewhere in every one of us is a deep longing to make contact with the unknown, with some “higher power” – something greater or wiser or more powerful than ourselves. This is true at all levels, from the teenage girl reading her horoscope, to the witch doctor in some remote tribe who has never seen a white man, to the scientist probing outer space and seeking to discover the secrets of the universe.

It was God who placed this longing within us, but His archenemy, Satan, has devised a way to divert seekers into deceptive, evil systems that bring them into bondage to himself. These deceptive systems can take countless different forms, but the generic name for them all is the occult. This raises the fourth question commonly asked concerning the realm of the demonic: What is the occult?

The word occult is derived from a Latin word that means “concealed” or “covered over.” The power operating through occult practices or systems derives from Satan and is evil. But most people caught up in them do not know this. They have been enticed by labels or claims that make them appear highly desirable.

This is vivid to me because of my own experience. I was fascinated, as I said in chapter 10, by all things connected with India, and at Cambridge I actually attempted to become a yogi. No matter how hard I tried, however, I could never attain the release or fulfilment I was searching for. This indefinable longing was finally satisfied when, by the grace of God, I had a supernatural encounter with Jesus, the Son of God.

Scripture calls turning away from the one true God to false gods “spiritual adultery.” Thus the Bible’s strong warnings against immorality and adultery also apply to all forms of involvement with the occult. The “strange [immoral or adulterous] woman” described in Proverbs vividly depicts the lure of the occult.

In Proverbs 5:6 we are warned against trying to study her ways, because they are “moveable” (kjv), “unstable” (nkjv) and “crooked” (niv) – all of which apply to the occult. I have observed that as one deceptive error is refuted, two new occult practices or false religions rise up in its place. Rather than attempt to give a full list, therefore, I will point out ways by which they operate. Truth is the best defence against error.

The tragic end of those who permit themselves to be enticed and deceived by a “strange woman” is described in Proverbs 7:25-27:

Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways,

Do not stray into her paths;

For she has cast down many wounded,

And all who were slain by her were strong men.

Her house is the way to hell,

Descending to the chambers of death.

Scripture emphasises that the victims of this “strange woman” are strong men. It is characteristic of these deceptive forces that they primarily target men with leadership capacity. Satan hates such men. Strong men become vulnerable when they place their confidence in their own strength and in their past successes.

The Two Main Branches of the Occult

The two main branches of the occult are identified in Scripture as divination and sorcery.

Divination

Divination provides knowledge through supernatural means about people, events and situations. Frequently it predicts future events. The contemporary terms for this are fortune-telling, psychic predicting and extrasensory perception (ESP).

A clear example is offered by the slave girl in Acts 16:16-22, who was said to be “possessed with a spirit of divination” (nkjv) or “a spirit by which she predicted the future” (niv). Actually the Greek merely says “she had a python spirit.” In classical Greek culture the python was often associated with the practice of divination or fortune-telling. The modern term for such a person is psychic.

This slave girl was the first person in Philippi to discern the identity of Paul and Silas. “These men are the servants of the Most High God,” she cried, “who proclaim to us the way of salvation” (verse 17). Everything she said was true, yet her knowledge came from a demon. When the demon was expelled, she lost the ability to tell fortunes and her masters lost their source of income.

This is what makes fortune-telling so deceptive and dangerous. A person – and it is usually a woman – who has a python spirit can actually be a channel of supernatural knowledge concerning the past or future. This measure of truth is the bait on Satan’s occult hook by which he seeks to capture and enslave his victims.

Fortune-telling (divination) is truly occult (hidden). It conceals the satanic source of the power. Among those who seek to know the future are highly placed political leaders – and even professing Christians. Yet that contact inevitably exposes them to demons. I will describe just a few examples from my own personal observation.

Mary had listened to one of my teachings and believed she was under demonic power. She was a member of an old-line church that adhered to the Gospel of Christ. But one day an older woman, considered the most spiritual in the church, came to Mary and said, “Let me read your palm.” When Mary acquiesced, the older woman told her, “You will have a baby, but it will be born dead.”

It happened just as she said. Mary’s baby was born with its umbilical cord wrapped twice around its neck and did not survive. By the sin of consulting a fortune-teller, albeit a professing Christian, I believe Mary opened the way for a satanic force that took the life of her baby.

Once Mary understood how she had exposed herself to demonic power, she was able to claim the benefit of Christ’s sacrifice on her behalf and be delivered. But that did not bring her baby back!

How many other churchgoing Christians have unknowingly been caught in Satan’s coils through fortune-telling?

The prediction of a psychic about the course of a person’s life often amounts to a declaration of Satan’s destiny for that life. In chapter 11 I mentioned that one main function of the daimons, who operate on the higher level, is to assign people their destiny – that is, Satan’s destiny for them. The daimon communicates this destiny through a daimonion operating on the earthly plane. (This is the essence of fortune-telling.)

This was brought home to me vividly while I was trying to help a woman who had come to me for deliverance. She told me she had been a spiritist but claimed she had repented. After praying for a while, I paused to seek direction from the Lord. Suddenly the woman turned to me and said, “I see you in a car and it’s wrecked against a tree.”

I stiffened. That’s the demon speaking! I said to myself.

Then I said aloud, “Satan, I refuse your destiny for my life. I shall not be in any car that’s wrecked against a tree.”

More than thirty years have passed since then, and it has never happened. Suppose, however, that I had allowed fear to enter, thinking, One day I’m going to be in a car that’s wrecked against a tree! I would have been accepting Satan’s destiny for my life, and I believe he might have killed me. I thank God I was alert.

A young Christian woman came to me once in great distress. A year or two previously, against her own better judgement, she had visited a fortune-teller who had told her, “You’re going to be a young widow.” Shortly afterward her husband was killed in a freak accident.

This young woman was overcome by guilt at the thought that her visit to the fortune-teller had somehow exposed her husband to the accident that had taken his life. She pleaded desperately with me to reassure her. I felt great compassion for her and did my best to comfort her, but I could not honestly give her the assurance she asked for. I could not rule out the possibility that she had, in fact, accepted Satan’s destiny for her husband and herself.

My own wife, Ruth, had an experience before she came to know Jesus as her Messiah. A friend told her about a psychic who had predicted certain things in his life, all of which had come to pass. He suggested that this woman could give help and comfort to Ruth, who was struggling as she raised three children alone. Ruth, an active member of her synagogue, had never heard anything forbidding fortune-telling.

The psychic, who had never seen Ruth before and knew nothing about her, told her three things: “You were not able to bear children; you have three adopted children; and your husband has left you.” Every one of those statements was correct. But the revelation did not come from God; it came from Satan. He intended to use this measure of truth as a bait to entice Ruth further into the occult.

In His mercy Jesus intervened in Ruth’s life. Later, when she realised her error, Ruth repented and cancelled Satan’s power over her.

My first wife, Lydia, used a simple illustration to warn people of Satan’s snare. “You can give me a glass of pure water,” she would say, “but if you put in just one drop of poison, the whole glass is poisoned.” No inspired “revelation” from a fortune-teller is worth having your whole life poisoned.

Country fairs, and even some churches, often have fortune-telling booths as a side show, “just for fun.” But there is no such thing as harmless fortune-telling. Poison is poison, even when it is not labelled.

Another form of this demonic activity can be even more deceptive. I call it “charismatic fortune-telling.” There are some ministers and speakers at conventions who offer personal prophecy and encourage Christians to come expecting “a word from the Lord.” Undoubtedly some words are from the Lord, but many more proceed from the soul of the person ministering or even from a demon of divination. This can have a disastrous effect on the lives of those who are ensnared by it.

Most people want to know what the future holds. Fortune-telling caters to this desire. But God requires us to “walk by faith, not by sight” (2 Corinthians 5:7), not knowing what the future holds but trusting His unfailing faithfulness. There may, however, be times when God will give us some sovereign revelation concerning the future, without our desiring or seeking it. When He takes the initiative, the result will serve His purposes.

Another snare, which poses as a game, is the Ouija board. I recall teaching on the nature of the occult in an Episcopal church in New England and praying for many who needed deliverance from demons. At the closing meeting on Sunday morning, the rector began by saying that his wife had asked him earlier in the day what had caused the smell of burning in their home. “It was me,” he went on, “burning our family Ouija board!”

The use of Ouija boards and other occult practices has now permeated many branches of our school systems. In one school a group of girls began playing with a Ouija board just as an experiment – to see what would happen. One day it spelled out this sentence: Within a week one of you will be dead. That week one of the girls was killed in an accident. The rest of the girls were terrified, not knowing what would happen next.

Another way many people are exposed to divination is through horoscopes. A generation or two ago, many newspapers carried a daily portion of Scripture. Today the same pages often carry a daily horoscope reading. Casually scanning “your” horoscope in the newspaper with an unguarded mind can expose you to demonic influence.

Here again, many Christians are deceived. They consider such activities harmless, not recognising the snare. I ministered to a Christian woman once who needed deliverance from a spirit of divination. She could not understand how such a spirit could have entered her. As I questioned her, she eventually acknowledged that she read her horoscope occasionally in the daily newspaper. She was shocked to realise that she had opened herself to a demon of divination.

Another potential door-opener for demons is involvement in the martial arts. Ruth and I ministered to a man who had excelled in karate. After a deliverance session, he discovered to his surprise that he could no longer do the karate kick. He had not realised that his ability came from a demon. We need to bear in mind that all the martial arts originated in cultures permeated with idolatry and demonic activity.

Sorcery

The other channel through which the occult operates is sorcery. Sorcery can be considered the twin sister of divination, but it has its own special sphere of activity. It uses various means to make an impact on the physical senses. Some of its tools are drugs, potions, charms, amulets, magic, spells, incantations and various forms of music.

In speaking of the last days, Paul warns that “evil men and impostors will grow worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived” (2 Timothy 3:13). The Greek word translated “impostors” means, literally, “enchanters,” but because enchanting (incantation) is used in various occult rituals, it came to mean “wizards” or “sorcerers.” Some contemporary forms of music, such as acid rock, fall into the same category and are used as channels of supernatural satanic power. This agrees with Paul’s prediction that, as the age draws to its close, there will be a great upsurge of these occult forces.

The book of Revelation describes two end-time judgements of God by which some sections of humanity will be killed. Then it closes by saying that “the rest of mankind . . . did not repent of their murders or their sorceries or their sexual immorality or their thefts” (Revelation 9:20-21). The Greek word translated “sorceries” means literally “drugs.” The niv renders it “magic arts.” The evil actions here associated with sorcery are murders, sexual immorality and theft. Often addiction to drugs opens the door to these other evils.

In Deuteronomy 18:10-12 the Lord declares His attitude towards various forms of occult involvement:

Let no one be found among you who sacrifices his son or daughter in the fire, who practices divination or sorcery, interprets omens, engages in witchcraft, or casts spells, or who is a medium or spiritist or who consults the dead. Anyone who does these things is detestable to the Lord. . . .

(niv)

The other main category mentioned here, in addition to divination and sorcery, is witchcraft, which also includes spells. I will deal more fully with witchcraft in the next chapter.

“Interpreting omens” is a form of divination. The last three categories – “a medium or a spiritist or [one] who consults the dead” – are all classed together today as spiritism. Their usual form of activity is called a séance.

All such people are said to be detestable to the Lord. The word translated “detestable” is the strongest word in the Hebrew language for what the Lord hates and rejects. Note, too, that God places such people in the same category as those who sacrifice their children to a pagan deity. It is hard for our contemporary culture to realise how intensely God hates all these occult practices. No one can be involved in them without being exposed to demons.

False Religion

Closely related to the occult is false religion. Often the two are inseparably intertwined. Both promise what appeals to us all – peace, power, knowledge, access to God. They claim to direct us to the light, but they actually entice us into darkness.

How, then, can we protect ourselves? In John 10:9 Jesus said, “I am the door. If anyone enters by Me, he will be saved . . . .” Again He said, “I am the way, the truth, and the life. No one comes to the Father except through Me” (John 14:6). Many different doors lead into the realm of the supernatural. But there is only one door that leads to the supernatural realm of God. That door is Jesus. Those who go through any other door can enter a supernatural realm – but it is the realm of Satan, not of the one true God.

Satan will do all the damage he can to humanity through ideologies such as atheism or humanism, but false religion is an infinitely more powerful tool in his hands. To this very hour, the great majority of the human race is enslaved by false religion.

As with other forms of the occult, it is impossible to list all the forms of false religion currently being practised. But here are some of the main features that characterise religions as false:

Acknowledging a plurality of gods
Practising idol worship in any form
Teaching that human beings can ultimately become gods
Teaching that people can achieve righteousness by their own efforts
Offering some form of esoteric knowledge available only to a privileged few

1. Religions That Acknowledge a Plurality of Gods

The early Church was surrounded by a polytheistic culture, but in 1 Corinthians 8:5-6 Paul defined the Christian position:

For even if there are so-called gods, whether in heaven or on earth (as there are many gods and many lords), yet for us there is only one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we for Him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and through whom we live.

2. Religions That Practice Idol Worship in Any Form

Idolatry is the first specific sin forbidden in the Ten Commandments and the one that carries the heaviest penalties (see Exodus 20:3-5).

3. Religions Teaching That Human Beings Ultimately Can Become Gods

This was the original temptation offered humanity by Satan in the Garden of Eden: “You will be like God [or like gods]” (Genesis 3:5).

This promise contains an inherent self-contradiction. God, who has created all things, including the human race, is Himself uncreated. It is logically impossible for man, the created, to become like God, the uncreated. The created can never become uncreated. Nevertheless, this promise of becoming like God has appealed to the self-exalting pride of humanity in every generation.

4. Religions Teaching That People Can Achieve Righteousness by Their Own Efforts

Again, the appeal is to human pride. Proud people are drawn to religious systems that demand hard, unreasonable forms of work and even self-inflicted suffering. The more rigorous the demands of a religion, the greater the degree of pride a person feels in fulfilling them.

5. Religions That Offer Some Form of Esoteric Knowledge Available Only to a Privileged Few

Access to this knowledge usually requires some special rite of initiation. Already in the first century, the apostles were warning their followers about this form of deception, called by its Greek name gnosis (knowledge). It was against this error that Paul warned Timothy:

O Timothy! Guard what was committed to your trust, avoiding the profane and vain babblings and contradictions of what is falsely called knowledge [gnosis] – by professing it, some have strayed concerning the faith.

1 Timothy 6:20-21

There are two outstanding contemporary examples of religions whose secrets are revealed only to those who have passed through a stringent process of initiation. They are Mormonism and Freemasonry. The latter includes Eastern Star (the women’s affiliate of Freemasonry), the Shriners, Rainbow Girls and Demolay.

In Mormonism the temple rituals are available only to a select few. No outsider may enter the temples while services are in progress. Freemasonry is even more secretive. Except for a few “official” public appearances, it is completely closed to the uninitiated and its secrets are guarded by bloodcurdling oaths.2

Biblical Christianity, on the other hand, is open. It has no special process of initiation and no secret rites. The basis of its faith, the Bible, is an open book. All are encouraged to study it.

All forms of false religion appeal in one way or another to human pride. The Gospel, on the other hand, emphasises that we are saved by the grace of God, which cannot be earned, but is received only by faith, which God Himself supplies. This leaves no room for pride.

For by grace you have been saved through faith, and that not of yourselves; it is the gift of God, not of works, lest anyone should boast.

Ephesians 2:8-9

There is a great gulf that cannot be bridged between the worship of the true God and every form of the occult or false religion. Paul emphasises that every form of false religion is permeated by demonic power and that Christians must not, therefore, be involved in any way:

. . . The things which the Gentiles sacrifice they sacrifice to demons and not to God, and I do not want you to have fellowship with demons. You cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons; you cannot partake of the Lord’s table and of the table of demons.

1 Corinthians 10:20-21

Anyone who has been involved in the occult or false religion needs to repent of it, confess it as sin and seek Christ for forgiveness, cleansing and release. In addition, any books or other objects connected with the occult or false religion should be destroyed.

Clean and Free

This brief overview of the whole area of the occult and false religions reveals just how complex and confusing it is. There is no simple way to define or describe it. You might compare it to an octopus with many tentacles, which it fastens onto its victim. Just as the victim is guarding himself against one tentacle, another seeks to fasten onto him from his blind side.

This is well illustrated by the following testimony of a young man from a Christian family who was taken captive by the occult. Eventually he gained understanding of the demonic realm, received deliverance and became a successful pastor.

My parents are godly, born-again Christians. Like little Samuel of old, I was dedicated to serve the Lord from my conception. My parents taught me in the ways of truth from my youth. At the age of four, I would stand and preach to my folks or anyone else who would listen. In my early years my heart was tender toward the things of God, and I was always quick to pray and repent when I wronged God or man. My precious parents taught me the best they could to walk in God’s ways, but they erred greatly because their tradition did not teach them that occult involvement was much worse than their traditional “thou-shalt-nots.”

To read the funny papers on Sunday, to go to a movie at any time or to condone drinking or smoking was unthinkable. But they never dreamed that allowing me to listen to ghost stories from my grandmother would start me on a path of heartache that would last over twenty years.

I first came into contact with my grandmother’s stories at the age of seven. From that point on I could find joy in little else but the study of the occult. Radio programmes of the ’40s and ’50s such as Inner Sanctum, The Shadow and The Whistler held my undivided attention. When TV came in, Night Gallery, Alfred Hitchcock and The Twilight Zone, plus any other kind of horror show, were my delight. By the time I was in the sixth grade, Edgar Allen Poe was my favourite author. A Baptist Training Union leader had introduced me to Poe’s writing after a church Halloween party.

At age eleven, I told God in one of my frequent rages to get out of my life and leave me alone. I would buy small animals on a weekly, sometimes daily, basis and torture them to death. (I did this out of sheer compulsion. Years later I found out it was an integral part of witchcraft.) As strange as it may seem, I loved animals and wanted to be a doctor of veterinary medicine.

I would walk up to Christian workers and tell them I hated them. No form of discipline, word or rod, could constrain me. Rebellion and utter hatred of God, church, Christians, school, all forms of authority, and especially my mother and father, ruled part of my being. The other part of me longed to be kind and loving.

I finally came to a saving knowledge of Jesus at the age of 25. Even though God intervened and I was born again, my relationship with my parents was very bad. I loved them because of Jesus, but I could not be civil toward them for more than an hour. After a short period of close fellowship, anger and hate would surface and my misery would spread to all those around me. I tried to suppress my inward pressures, but they showed themselves by my craving for alcohol and food. I was 5’ 7 1/2’’ and weighed 217 pounds.

Was I really saved? Yes! Yes! Yes! I would spend hours weeping over lost souls, memorising Scripture, witnessing and teaching the Word. What was so tragic was that still no one had ever told me that ESP, Ouija boards and books on psychic phenomena were forbidden to me as a believer. Therefore, I taught these to my First Baptist Church Training Union class, thus stirring up in them the same idolatry and witchcraft my grandmother had stirred up in me years before.

Praise the Lord, one day as I told a fellow believer about my ESP, he told me to leave it alone, as Scripture warned against it. Oh, how I thank God for that man! His simple warning helped me begin on the path to deliverance.

Wanting to obey the Lord, I stopped all contact with the satanic realm. This was a good beginning, but what I really needed was complete renunciation of Satan and deliverance from the demons that had entered because of my interest in the occult.

How do I know I had demons? The day I stopped flirting with Satan and started obeying the Word, my internal problems and fears intensified. The anger and hate got worse. I began to have hallucinations night and day that presented the Jesus I loved in a most defiling way. Though I was happily married, my problem with masturbation was uncontrollable. My greatest plague was that I was a latent homosexual. I never gave in to it, though I had to fight it constantly. I would have horrible thoughts of being with men, and desires to dress like a woman. When I was alone, this evil spirit would manifest and I would take on effeminate mannerisms.

I hated and loathed these things with all my might. I prayed, repented and tried to crucify the flesh, not realising that my problems had gone past the earthly, past the soulish, into the demonic (James 3:15). I had two fountains within me: One loved souls, blessed God and yearned to serve Him. The other defiled me with unclean thoughts and desires, blasphemed Jesus and cursed the saints. I would have willingly admitted all this to anyone who could have helped me. No one I knew had the power to deal with my problems, even to the point of listening to them. So I had to keep it all in as best I could.

In December 1969 my wife and I were introduced to the deliverance ministry. When it was mentioned that Christians could have demons, I gave no argument. My spirit leaped for joy, as I knew I had found the answer to my problems. A brother in Christ ministered deliverance to me, commanding the spirits to leave. I literally felt them move up from my stomach through my mouth, coming out in sighs and yawns.

From that day to this, I have never been plagued with masturbation. Plus my anger and hate were gone. Now I can spend hours with my mother with no schisms. I can actually hug her with love and compassion.

For several months I was on cloud nine. Then suddenly the latent homosexuality and hallucinations started again. To be exact, it was about two o’clock one morning when I was awakened by demonic harassment from within and without. By this time I knew how to cast out demons and resist Satan, but my relief was only temporary.

Just when I was about to lose hope, I heard a Derek Prince tape saying occult sins had to be confessed and renounced by name. This was something I had not done. I immediately did so, realising where most of my problems had come from. Shortly after this I went through my greatest deliverance service.

One day I was driving from Columbus, Georgia, to Montgomery, Alabama (a little over one hundred miles). During a time of horrible harassment by demons, I called on Jesus with all my might. He took me back in mental visions to instances that began at age four when demons first entered me. As He showed me each instance, I would renounce the sins involved and command the demon to come out. For more than an hour, demons came out of my mouth, the top of my head and shoulders. By the time I got to Montgomery, I felt wrung out, but I was free – free for the first time in years.

Since that time my spiritual growth has progressed rapidly. My time and energy can be directed toward fruitful ministry rather than wrestling continually to suppress desires and thoughts that used to threaten my very existence. Also the Lord has taken me from 217 pounds to 155 happy pounds.

Praise the Lord! Because of Jesus, I am clean and free.

2. For more information see Masonry – Beyond the Light by William Schnoebelen (Chick Publications, 1991).

20

Demons of Sickness and Infirmity

Another area we need to consider is the body. In chapter 3 I pointed out that Jesus made no hard-and-fast distinction between healing sickness and expelling demons.

Luke describes the first occasion that Jesus ministered to the sick:

All those who had anyone sick with various diseases brought them to Him; and He laid His hands on every one of them and healed them. And demons also came out of many, crying out and saying, “You are the Christ, the Son of God!”

Luke 4:40-41

This account makes it clear that many of their sicknesses were caused by demons.

Demons can, I believe, be the cause of almost every kind of physical pain and sickness, but it takes discernment to distinguish between sicknesses or pains that have a demonic cause and those that are purely physical. With our limited understanding, we may find it difficult to envisage how a spiritual entity such as a demon can occupy a physical space, such as an area of the human body. But whether we understand it or not, the fact is that it happens and that it is depicted frequently in Scripture.

The gospels record that Jesus healed the mute, deaf and blind by expelling demons (see Matthew 9:32-33; 12:22; Luke 11:14). In Luke 13:11-16 Jesus met a woman who had suffered from what we might call spinal curvature or scoliosis for eighteen years. Although her condition seemed to be purely physical, Jesus declared that she had been bound by a “spirit of infirmity.” On that basis He set her free and she was completely healed. In Mark 9:17-29 Jesus dealt with a boy who had the symptoms of epilepsy. He confronted it, however, as “a dumb and deaf spirit” (verse 25). When the demon was expelled, the boy was healed.

Nearly two thousand years have passed, but the same principles still apply. Over more than thirty years, I have seen hundreds healed from many kinds of sickness or infirmity through deliverance from demons. I will mention just a few cases.

Epilepsy

In the early 1970s a young woman of eighteen came to Lydia and me for prayer. She had been diagnosed with epilepsy, which was controlled by medication. When she heard some of my teaching, she wondered if her epilepsy might be caused by an evil spirit.

When Lydia and I prayed for her and commanded the demon of epilepsy to leave her, it came out. But then I felt the Lord telling me, Your job isn’t finished. So I asked the girl, “How did your seizures start? Was it through a physical injury?”

“Yes,” she replied. “I was struck on the head by a baseball, and after that the seizures started.”

I explained to her that the physical injury opened the “door” by which the spirit of epilepsy entered. “Now that the spirit has gone out,” I said, “we need to close the door so that it can’t come in again.”

So Lydia and I laid hands on her head and prayed for the healing of her brain.

We remained in contact with the young woman for about two years. During that time she took no further medication and suffered no further seizures.

A few years ago another woman came to me with her daughter of about eighteen.

“Mr. Prince,” she said, “ten years ago you prayed for me and I was delivered from the spirit of epilepsy. Here’s my daughter. She has the same problem. Please pray for her.”

Ruth and I prayed for the daughter, commanding the demon of epilepsy to leave, and she was healed, just as her mother had been.

A friend of mine, an evangelist, was asked to pray for someone with epilepsy. When he came against the epileptic spirit, the spirit – not the person – replied, “You fool! I’ve been medically certified.”5

Demons know how to adapt to modern medical procedure and terminology!

I should add here that two members of our large combined family, not related to one another, have received healing from epilepsy through prayer without any outward manifestation – so Jesus still has different ways to deal with people today!

When people come to me for prayer for deliverance from epilepsy, I usually tell them, “You need to know that the demon may put up a fight before it leaves. Are you prepared to fight for yourself? If so, I’ll fight together with you and we’ll win. But if you are not prepared to fight for yourself, I’m not going to fight on my own.” In every case that I can remember, the person has been willing to fight, and God has given us the victory. I have no faith, however, for people who simply remain passive, without taking their own stand against the enemy.

As a general rule, I do not pray for those who expect to be released only on the basis of my prayers. A person unwilling to take an active stand against the demon will probably not have the defences to keep it from returning. Matthew 12:43-45 warns us that the evil spirit will return, bringing “seven other spirits more wicked than himself . . . and the last state of that man is worse than the first.” The experience of Esther described in chapter 6 provides an example of demons trying to return. (In chapter 23 I will give instructions about how to stay free.)

Blindness, Deafness, Muteness and Arthritis

In Hawaii a young man brought to Ruth and me his grandmother, who was about eighty and blind. She was from French-speaking Switzerland, and her mother tongue was French. Although I was not conscious of having any great faith, Ruth and I began to pray for her. Then, speaking in English, I commanded the spirit of blindness to leave the woman. After a few moments, the woman turned to me and said in French, “Je vous vois” (“I can see you”). I was both amazed and delighted!

In 1985 Ruth and I led a ministry team to Pakistan. Because it had been advertised that we would pray for the sick, people came from all over Pakistan. Most of them were illiterate and quite undisciplined. One day the women, who in that culture are seated separately, were extremely noisy and disorderly. Seeking to establish some discipline, I announced, “This morning we will pray only for men.”

Immediately about two hundred men rushed up to our team, all wanting prayer. Ruth and I encountered a man who touched first his lips, then his ears, indicating that he was a deaf mute. Recalling that Jesus had expelled an evil spirit from a deaf mute, I decided to do the same. I cannot say I had any special faith.

“You deaf mute spirit,” I said, “in the name of Jesus, I command you to come out of this man.”

I knew the man could not hear me, nor would he understand English. But the demon understood!

When I said to the man, “Now say hallelujah,” he opened his mouth and shouted, “Hallelujah!” I took him to the leader on the platform, who began to tell the people in Urdu about the miracle.

This report stirred up faith, and people began to bring other deaf mutes to us. (In a Muslim nation there is an unusually high proportion of such cases.) In the next few minutes Ruth and I cast out deaf mute spirits from at least ten more men or boys, and all were healed. One exciting case was a boy of about five whose first word was umma (mama).

In 1980, at a large conference in South Africa, I was asked to conduct a seminar on healing and deliverance for about a thousand people. The first day I taught on healing, then began praying individually for the sick. The power of God was present and there were several dramatic healings.

Then a woman came forward with arthritis. I said to her, “I believe that your arthritis is a demon. Are you prepared to have it cast out?”

She nodded, so Ruth and I laid hands on her and commanded the demon of arthritis to go. Within a few minutes she said, “All my pain has gone! I’m healed.”

As the people applauded and thanked Jesus, I sensed that their collective faith had risen so that it was no longer necessary to minister to each person individually. I asked all those suffering from arthritis to stand. About thirty people all over the auditorium rose to their feet. After explaining to them what I intended to do, I took authority over every demon of arthritis and commanded them to go in the name of Jesus. Then I told the people standing not to sit down until their pain had left and they knew they were healed.

As Ruth and I went on praying for people with other sicknesses, those with arthritis began to sit down one by one. After about fifteen minutes, none was left standing.

Some weeks later, travelling around South Africa, Ruth and I met several of these people individually, and they confirmed to us that they had been healed that day.

Death

In chapter 6 I recounted that both Esther and her daughter, Rose, were delivered from a spirit of death. The spirit had entered Esther when she had nearly died on the operating table – a moment of special weakness. We need to remember that Satan is a murderer (see John 8:44). He uses the spirit of death to kill a person who would not die through purely natural causes.

This was corroborated by a Christian doctor, head of a clinic, who came to me after a meeting. “What you taught us about the spirit of death,” he said, “has helped me understand people who die without our finding any sufficient medical cause of death. Now I realise that they are victims of the spirit of death.”

One of my grandsons, himself a minister, had an amazing experience. Here is his testimony:

Our daughter, Rebecca, was born with a hole in her heart. When she was six, in January 1993, she had open heart surgery to repair it.

We were permitted to visit the Intensive Care ward for only ten minutes every hour. Before entering the ward, it was necessary to obtain permission from the head nurse. One morning we were waiting in the hallway with twenty other anxious parents. When we were refused entry, we realised something was amiss. I picked up the house phone to inquire, and the nurse replied that they were having difficulties with one of the children and that we would have to continue to wait. I told the other parents, and every face went pale. Suddenly the double door swung open and out came the doctor and hospital chaplain. They spoke to the couple standing opposite us, and immediately the mother burst into tears. They were ushered quickly into the counselling room.

Shortly after this traumatic scene, we all were allowed to enter and visit our children. When we entered the ward, we noticed a doctor standing at the foot of the bed right next to our daughter. The twelve-year-old boy in the bed, who had undergone surgery that morning, was the son of that couple! Glancing at his heart monitor, we saw that it was a flat line.

Standing between the two beds, I grabbed my wife’s hand and said in a low voice, with urgency, “I come against the spirit of death in this place in the name of Jesus.” Our attention then turned toward our daughter, who was awake and in need of our care.

The next morning, as I was walking down the corridor, I saw the boy’s father with a smile on his face. I stopped and asked him what had happened. The father told me in amazement, “The doctors had given my son no hope, and just like that he turned around. This morning he sat up in bed and gave me two thumbs up!”

My wife and I both know God delivered that boy from the spirit of death. Thank God we knew what to do!

Natural or Demonic? Discerning the Cause

In the previous chapters I have spoken about lying spirits that attack people’s minds. In 1994 Ruth and I experienced a different kind of attack from lying spirits. After battling a series of major illnesses for several years, Ruth had received a word from the Lord: Your time of sickness is over. A few weeks later, on a day we had set aside for prayer and fasting, Ruth was attacked by pain in every area of her body, from her head to her feet. She said, “O Lord, please, not again!”

Through these years Ruth and I have learned not to give way to infirmity, but to stand on God’s promises. So she said to me, “I know I would feel better if I could worship the Lord, but I don’t have the strength. Would you put on the Russian worship cassette from the conference we did in Moscow last year? I believe it will help me.”

Ruth was on the floor of our bedroom, and as she began to relax and worship the Lord, she exclaimed, “These are lying symptoms – lying spirits – trying to steal God’s promise from me!”

When we took our stand together, in the name of Jesus, against those lying spirits, Ruth was completely delivered from pain.

In God’s amazing grace, He went on to grant us a special serendipity for which there is no natural explanation. In Ruth’s words:

I rose to my feet and went to the kitchen for a glass of water. Suddenly Derek called to me, “Come quickly!” When I returned to the bedroom, I gasped! The whole room and adjoining bath were fragrant with the scent of roses – like an English garden. It was as if the Lord Himself was there. I fell on my face on the floor in adoration.

God had made Ruth and me “more than conquerors” (Romans 8:37). We came out of that trial with more than we had when we went into it.

This experience brought to my mind other Christians who had received a genuine healing from the Lord, against whom Satan had apparently directed lying spirits to undermine their faith and destroy their testimony. We need to “put on the whole armour of God, that [we] may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil” (Ephesians 6:11).

I need to emphasise, however, as I said in chapter 10, that not all sicknesses are caused by demons. Many have other, natural causes. This makes it important to identify sicknesses that are directly caused by demons.

In 1 Corinthians 12 Paul lists nine supernatural gifts of the Holy Spirit available to believers. Of these there are two that may help us to identify demons: literally, a word of knowledge and discernings of spirits (see verses 8, 10).

I have given a literal translation of these two phrases because the text indicates that each word of knowledge and each act of discerning is an individual gift. Each, too, operates on a supernatural plane, not as the product of natural reasoning or intelligence.

In Hebrews 4:12 the writer says:

For the word of God is living and powerful, and sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing even to the division of soul and spirit, and of joints and marrow, and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart.

It is this kind of insight that can come through a word of knowledge. It can penetrate the invisible areas of human personality and reveal the identity of evil forces lurking there. Often the revelation comes in the form of a single word or phrase impressed on the mind of the person ministering deliverance, or sometimes of the one receiving deliverance. A demon thus identified might be colitis, crippling, asthma, schizophrenia or cancer.

The presence of a demon, however, may not necessarily be revealed supernaturally. It may simply come about in the normal course of personal counselling, in the same way that a doctor may diagnose a disease from the symptoms a patient describes. This chapter and the preceding nine provide a fairly comprehensive survey of some of the most common symptoms of demonic activity. One thing I have found particularly helpful is to identify, if possible, the moment or place of weakness through which a demon gained entrance.

There is another way demons can be contributory causes of sickness. In chapter 19 I spoke about negative emotional spirits. While not actually causing sickness, they can produce an attitude of mind that either opens the door to sickness or else prevents sick people from receiving their healing by faith. Some examples of such negative spirits are rejection, fear, grief, unforgiveness, discouragement, disappointment and despair. In such cases, it is usually necessary to expel the negative spirit before seeking to minister physical healing.

I have related just a few of the occasions on which I have seen the authority of Christ used with great effectiveness against demons of sickness and infirmity. But I still regret the many occasions on which I did not follow the pattern of Christ’s aggressive approach to such demons. I have learned that moving on this supernatural plane requires continuing, day-to-day dependence on God, trusting Him for discernment and authority. In this ministry we must affirm with Paul that “we walk by faith, not by sight” (2 Corinthians 5:7).

Deliverance from Multiple Sclerosis and Stroke

I will close this chapter with two remarkable accounts of people delivered from demons of sickness or infirmity. The first comes from a lay worker in an American church:

A young woman from our church – we will call her Jane – had developed multiple sclerosis (MS). She heard teaching on faith, claimed her healing and was greatly improved. But she continued to have symptoms and to stumble while on her feet. She testified to her healing during a church service, but added, “I still stumble some, and I know there is something more I need.”

Jane and her sister came to us for prayer about 2:30 one afternoon. She said they had gone through all the prayers to obtain release. Then we started to work. Jane named at least one hundred spirits. I was too busy to count them. I have recalled a lot but not all of them. We worked from three until 6:15 p.m.

I thought there would be a spirit of MS, but instead she named spirits of all the symptoms: tiredness, weakness, stumbling, trembling, crying, weeping, mourning, blindness, deafness, choking, suffocation, coldness, paralysis, numbness, torment, fatigue, laziness, idleness, headaches, ear pain and more!

As we prayed, all the manifestations of MS grabbed her body, preventing her from standing. She also said she was numb all over. As the spirits came out, she would tell me what part of her body was getting warm and having the sense of feeling return.

She got free to her waist and to her hips, then to her knees and legs. Finally she said, “The remaining ones are in my feet.” She took off her boots; her feet felt rigid and cold. She would tell us as the demons were leaving her feet. Finally she said, “There are just two more in my toe.” I do not remember the first one, but the second one was “complaining.” When it left, she jumped up and danced around the room. Jane was totally freed from MS.

The other remarkable account of deliverance from a demon of sickness comes from a New Zealand evangelist with an international ministry:

On June 10, 1992, while I was conducting a meeting in Katikati, New Zealand, the Lord drew my attention to a woman with crutches, whom I called up to the stage. She climbed the stairs with difficulty.

She was in terrible pain, she said. She had bad osteoarthritis, circulation trouble in her heart and had suffered from diabetes for 41 years. She had also had a stroke after losing her husband two years earlier. The left side of her body had been affected. She limped, was unable to write properly and was hardly able to converse. She loved singing but her throat was contracted. In her youth, she added, she had had trouble with her periods, and had her first D&C – dilation and curettage – at age fourteen. Later she had had miscarriages.

I commanded every spirit affecting her to flee, particularly the spirit of stroke. Following my prayer she almost ran down the stairs from the platform. Her hands were in the air and she was clearly full of the Holy Spirit.

Three years later, on June 14, 1995, she came to another meeting in a nearby town and testified.

As she had gone back to her seat in Katikati, she told us, she had felt God’s healing. For the next week she had experienced jolts in her body as though something was moving in and out. Now she was able to run up and down the stairs. She was able to write, and the left side of her body was totally healed from the effects of the stroke, including her eye. And after three years the doctors still could find no trace of the diabetes she had had for 41 years.

Unquestionably she had received a miracle as the demonic power was cast out.

5. In fact, there is another “medically certified” demon called Tourette‘s syndrome, by which people mutter curses and oaths in public against their will.

23

How To Keep Your Deliverance

Thank God you have received deliverance! Continue to thank God! Even if you are not sure yet of all that has happened, you can express your faith by thanking Him. This is the first step to help you keep your deliverance.

You can be sure, however, that Satan will not give up on you. He will do everything in his power to reassert his control over you. You must be prepared for his counter-attack. I have referred several times to the warning of Jesus that a demon that has gone out of a man will seek to return. You must make completely sure, therefore, that Jesus is dwelling in you and that He is absolute Lord of your life.

We have seen that human personality is like a city, and that demonic invasion can have the effect of breaking down the walls inside us that should protect us. Once our enemy has been driven out, we must begin immediately to rebuild our protective walls. Here are the basic principles to help you rebuild:

Live by God’s Word
Put on the garment of praise
Come under discipline
Cultivate right fellowship
Be filled with the Holy Spirit
Make sure you have passed through the water of baptism
Put on the whole armour of God

1. Live by God’s Word

In Matthew 4:4 Jesus said that mankind shall live “by every word that proceeds from the mouth of God.” The word live is all-inclusive, covering everything we think, say or do. All must proceed from the same source: the Word of God. We must give it unchallenged pre-eminence in every area of our lives.

Many other influences will compete for control over us: our own feelings, the opinions of others, accepted traditions, the culture that surrounds us. But God guarantees us victory in every area – and specifically, victory over the devil – only insofar as our lives are directed and controlled by His Word.

Take to heart the directions the Lord gave to Joshua as he was about to enter the Promised Land:

“This Book of the Law shall not depart from your mouth, but you shall meditate in it day and night, that you may observe to do according to all that is written in it. For then you will make your way prosperous, and then you will have good success.”

Joshua 1:8

These directions may be summed up in three phrases: think the Word of God; speak the Word of God; act the Word of God. Then God guarantees you success.

2. Put On the Garment of Praise

In Isaiah 61:3 God offers us “the garment of praise” in place of “the spirit of heaviness.” In chapter 4 I related how I was delivered from depression when it was identified as a spirit of heaviness. After that I gradually learned that when I was praising the Lord, the spirit of heaviness would not come near me. I saw that I needed to cultivate a lifestyle in which praise would cover me as completely as the clothes I wore.

Once when Lydia and I were having an informal prayer meeting in our home in London, a woman from our congregation came to our door, leading a man by the hand.

“This is my husband,” she said. “He’s just out of prison and needs to be delivered from a demon.”

At that time I had no experience in ministering deliverance to others and no idea how to do it. So I simply invited him to join our prayer meeting. Some of our members were offering loud, uninhibited praise to the Lord.

After a while the man sidled up to me and said, “There’s too much noise. I’m going!”

“It’s the devil that doesn’t like the noise,” I replied, “because we’re praising Jesus. You’ve got two options. If you go now, the demon will go with you. If you stay, it will go without you.”

“I’ll stay,” he mumbled.

A little later he approached me again and said, “It’s just gone! I felt it leave my throat.”

You, having received deliverance, are also “just out of prison.” Enjoy your liberty! Do as the Word of God says: Put on the garment of praise. When you are praising the Lord, you trouble the devil more than he can trouble you.

3. Come under Discipline

Jesus’ last order to His apostles was to “go . . . and make disciples. . .” (Matthew 28:19). A disciple, as the word indicates, is one who is under discipline. Jesus never instructed anyone to make “church members.”

Because “rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft” (1 Samuel 15:23), and because rebellion against God has exposed our whole race to the deceptive and destructive power of Satan, we can come under God’s protection only as we place ourselves under His discipline. An undisciplined life is vulnerable to demonic attack.

In 2 Timothy 1:7 Paul says God has given us “a spirit of power, of love and of self-discipline” (niv). This is the primary form of discipline in any life – self-discipline. Unless we learn to discipline ourselves, no other form of discipline will be effective.

The first area in which this applies is our personal communion with God in His Word and in prayer. Living by God’s Word demands that we give Him regular “prime time” each day. Then, with the help of the Holy Spirit, we must bring our emotions, desires and appetites under control. A man not in control in these areas is not in control of his life.

There is one decisive area we must bring under control: the tongue. In chapter 13 I pointed out that idle words open the way for demons. The control of the tongue is the mark of spiritual maturity: “If anyone does not stumble in word, he is a perfect man, able also to bridle the whole body” (James 3:2).

Obviously you will not achieve this level of self-discipline in a few simple steps. From time to time you will stumble. Just pick yourself up, dust yourself off and continue to move forward and upward. As long as you are moving in the right direction, Satan may harass you but he cannot defeat you.

There are various other areas in which we may need to come under discipline, relating to the family, school, church and various forms of secular government. God requires us to cultivate submissiveness in any of these areas that apply in our lives: “Submit yourselves for the Lord’s sake to every authority instituted among men. . .” (1 Peter 2:13, niv).

It is true that deliverance brings us freedom, but many Christians misunderstand the nature of freedom. We are not free to do our own thing; we are free that we may bring every area of our lives under God’s discipline.

4. Cultivate Right Fellowship

I pointed out in chapters 15 and 19 that a person whose walls have been broken down by demons needs the help of other Christians to stand with him as he builds up those walls.

We need to recognise that one of the most powerful influences in our lives is the people with whom we associate. This means we have to choose the kind of people we spend time with. We may live among unbelievers, but we cannot make ourselves one with them. There must always be a difference between our lifestyle and theirs.

If we are walking in the light, we will have fellowship with our fellow believers (see 1 John 1:7). There is no place for self-centred individualism in the Christian life. As Christians we need each other. The writer of Hebrews gives us an urgent warning:

And let us consider one another in order to stir up love and good works, not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together, as is the manner of some, but exhorting one another, and so much the more as you see the Day approaching.

Hebrews 10:24-25

On the other hand, we are also warned, “Evil company corrupts good habits” (1 Corinthians 15:33). If you sincerely desire to keep your deliverance, you must break off relationships that have a wrong influence on you, and begin to cultivate friends who will encourage you and set you a good example. It may be painful to sever ties with friends or to dissociate yourself for a time from family members whose influence is harmful. But you can trust the Holy Spirit to help you do it with grace and wisdom and to take care of the consequences. Remember, He is your Helper!

5. Be Filled with the Holy Spirit

In Ephesians 5:18 Paul gives us two words of instruction. The first is negative: “Do not be drunk with wine.” The second is positive: “Be filled with the Spirit.” Most Christians would acknowledge that it is wrong to be drunk. Yet how many believe it is equally wrong not to be filled with the Spirit?

The infilling of the Holy Spirit is an essential part of God’s provision for victorious living. Paul speaks of this infilling in the continuing present tense: “Be continuously filled.” He is speaking not about a one-time experience but, in the next three verses, about a lifestyle:

Singing praises continually to the Lord
Being unceasingly thankful to God the Father
Being humbly submissive to one another

As the Holy Spirit fills you continuously in this way, demons will find in you no vacant area that they can occupy!

6. Make Sure You Have Passed through the Water of Baptism

Jesus told His apostles to “preach the gospel to every creature. He who believes and is baptised [immersed] will be saved. . .” (Mark 16:15-16). Baptism in water is not an option – some ecclesiastical ceremony that follows salvation. On the contrary, it is an outward act of obedience expressing the inward work of faith in our hearts, and thus making salvation complete. In the book of Acts there is no record of anyone receiving salvation without afterward being baptised in water.

In the New Testament, baptism is compared to two events in Old Testament history: Noah and his family in the ark passing through the waters of the flood (see Genesis 7-8; 1 Peter 3:19-21); and Israel escaping from the dominion of Pharaoh by passing through the Red Sea (see Exodus 14:15-31; 1 Corinthians 10:1-2). In each case passing through the water was an act of separation. Noah and his family were saved from the ungodly world that perished under God’s judgement, and Israel finally escaped Pharaoh’s oppression, since the Egyptian army could not follow them through the water.

There were two phases in Israel’s salvation. First, in Egypt they were saved from God’s judgement by faith in the blood of the Passover lamb, which was a type of Christ. Second, they were delivered from Egypt by passing through the Red Sea.

This pattern applies to us as Christians. We are saved in the world by faith in the blood of Jesus. But we are separated from the world by passing through the water of baptism. It is the act of being baptised that cuts us off from the kingdom of Satan. His demons have no right to follow us through the water.

If you have never been baptised in water as a believer, this is an important step you need to take to cut off demonic activity. If you have already been baptised, on the other hand, you need to stand fast on that fact and be confident that Satan’s demons have no further right of access to you. (I deal more thoroughly with this subject in my book Foundations for Righteous Living in the section “New Testament Baptisms.”)

7. Put On the Whole Armour of God

Now that you are wearing your garment of praise, God offers you a complete set of armour to put on over it. In case you have not yet realised it, you are a soldier in a war. You need all the armour God has provided for you.

The items of your equipment are listed in Ephesians 6:13-18, as follows:

The girdle [belt] of truth
The breastplate of righteousness
The shoes of the preparation of the gospel of peace
The shield of faith
The helmet of salvation
The sword of the Spirit – the word [Greek rhema] of God
All prayer

We will go through these items of armour in order.

The Girdle [Belt] of Truth

In biblical times men usually wore loose clothing that hung down below their knees. Before undertaking any strenuous activity, they would gather up their loose garment above their knees and fasten it with a belt around the waist. Hence the phrase that occurs several times in the Bible: Gird up your loins.

Likewise you must gather up and fasten out of the way anything that would impede your freedom to follow Jesus. The “belt” that enables you to do this is God’s Word, applied in a very plain and practical way. You must become totally sincere and open and put aside every form of dishonesty or hypocrisy. You must love the truth.

The Breastplate of Righteousness

The breastplate protects your most critical and vulnerable area: your heart. This righteousness is not mere intellectual assent to a doctrine: “With the heart” – not with the head – “one believes to righteousness” (Romans 10:10). Saving faith in the heart transforms a life of sin into a life of righteousness – not a righteousness that comes from following a set of religious rules, but from Christ dwelling in our hearts and living out His life through us.

“The righteous are bold as a lion” (Proverbs 28:1). This kind of righteousness transforms timidity into boldness, doubt into confidence.

The Shoes of the Preparation of the Gospel of Peace

Your shoes make you mobile. You must be available to God at any time or place to share the Gospel with those God puts in your way. In a world of strife and tension, you must be a vessel of God’s peace.

The Shield of Faith

The shield alluded to in Ephesians 6 was big enough to give protection to a soldier’s whole body, but it was effective only when he had learned how to use it.

You, too, must learn to use your faith as a shield to protect your whole person – spirit, soul and body – from Satan’s fiery darts. Remember, the shield will not merely ward off the flaming darts; it will extinguish them!

The Helmet of Salvation

The helmet protects the head – that is, the mind. Satan will direct more attacks against your mind than against any other area of your personality. The helmet is also called “the hope of salvation” (1 Thessalonians 5:8) – not mere wishful thinking, but an attitude of steady, continuing optimism based firmly on the truth of God’s Word.

In chapter 4 I described how God taught me to put on this helmet.

The Sword of the Spirit – the Word [Greek rhema] of God

Rhema means primarily a spoken word. The Bible on your bookshelf will not protect you. God’s Word becomes a sword when you speak it through your mouth in faith. Remember how Jesus used that sword against Satan, answering every temptation by quoting Scripture: “It is written. . . .” You must learn to do the same.

The sword is provided by the Holy Spirit, but it is your responsibility to take it. When you do, the Spirit provides supernatural power with which to wield it.

The Final Weapon: All Prayer

With the sword you are limited by the length of your arm. But “all prayer” is your intercontinental ballistic missile. By this kind of prayer you can reach across oceans and continents and strike the forces of Satan wherever they are at work. You can even reach out against Satan’s headquarters in the heavenlies. But it takes discipline and maturity to learn to use such a powerful weapon.

The Divine Paradox

Perhaps you feel a little overwhelmed as you consider what you must do to maintain your deliverance. You may feel inclined to say, “Can’t you put it more simply, in just a few words?”

Yes, all that I have said above can be expressed in one simple instruction: To keep your deliverance, all you have to do is live the Christian life as it is depicted and demonstrated in the New Testament. That is the distillation of how to keep your deliverance – but it is radical!

In Matthew 16:24-25 Jesus lays down two unvarying requirements for all who would follow Him:

“If anyone desires to come after Me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow Me. For whoever desires to save his life [literally, soul] will lose it, and whoever loses his life [literally, soul] for My sake will find it.”

Here is the divine paradox: to save (protect) our souls, we must lose them.6

Before we can follow Jesus, there are two preliminary steps. First we must deny ourselves; we must say a resolute and final No! to the demanding, self-seeking ego. Second, we must each take up our own cross. We must accept the sentence of death that the cross imposes on us. Taking up the cross is a voluntary decision that each of us must make. God does not forcefully impose the cross upon us.

If we do not apply the cross personally in our own lives, we leave a door open to demonic influence. There is always the danger that the uncrucified ego will respond to the seductive flatteries of deceiving demons. Pride is the main area in our character that Satan targets, and flattery is the main lever he uses to gain entrance.

We must each apply the cross personally to ourselves. In Galatians 2:20 Paul says, “I have been crucified with Christ; it is no longer I who live. . . .” We each need to ask: Is that true of me? Have I really been crucified with Christ? Or am I still motivated by my soulish ego?

Many Christians today would feel that this solution is too radical. They would question whether this is really the only way to be secure from deception. They tend to regard Paul as some kind of “super-saint” whom they could never hope to imitate.

Paul, however, did not see himself this way. His ministry as an apostle was unique, but his personal relationship with Christ was a pattern for all to follow. In 1 Timothy 1:16 he said:

However, for this reason I obtained mercy, that in me first Jesus Christ might show all long-suffering, as a pattern to those who are going to believe on Him for everlasting life.

Again in 1 Corinthians 11:1 he said, “Imitate me, just as I also imitate Christ.”

The only alternative to the cross is to put self in the place of Christ. But this is idolatry and opens the way for the evil consequences that invariably follow idolatry.

The cross is the heart and centre of the Christian faith. Without the cross proclaimed and applied, Christianity is left without a foundation, and its claims are no longer valid. It has become, in fact, a false religion. As such, like all false religions, it is inevitably exposed to demonic infiltration and deception.

Let me close this chapter with one final comment. I have come to see that my experiences over the years in dealing with demons have had a profound impact on my own Christian life. Time and time again I have come up against the blunt, uncompromising words of Jesus.

I have come to see that in the Christian life there are no shortcuts and no detours. If we desire immunity from demonic oppression, it is available to us on one condition only: obedience.

6. The next eight paragraphs are quoted from my booklet Protection from Deception.

Part 2

In the School of Experience

Personal experience by itself is never a sufficient basis for establishing biblical doctrine. At times, however, it can have the effect of illuminating a doctrine that previously one did not know how to apply.

This was true in my personal confrontation with demons. I had read the New Testament accounts of Jesus and His disciples dealing with demons, and accepted them as part of the revelation of Scripture. But they had never come alive to me.

I had often had the joy of leading a sinner to Christ. I had also seen people healed physically in answer to prayer. But I had no conscious experience of confronting and dealing with demons, with the outward manifestations described so vividly in the New Testament.

Then God in His sovereignty began to give me direct personal experience in recognising and dealing with demons. First of all, I myself received release from persistent, crippling bouts of depression when I recognised the source behind them and called out to God for deliverance. Later I encountered demons manifesting in other people, and proved in my own experience the truth of Jesus’ promise to His disciples in Mark 16:17: “In My name they will cast out demons.” This added an important new dimension to my ministry.

Looking back, I realise God had enrolled me in His “school of experience,” guiding me sovereignly from one demonic encounter to the next. In the end, dealing with demons became a regular part of my Christian ministry.

In the chapters that follow, I share some of the most important lessons God taught me on the path by which He led me.